Guide to the Marcia Citron Papers, 1969-2014 MS 633
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Marcia Citron Papers
1969-2014
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Citron, Marcia J.
MS 633
1 Linear Feet
This collection contains the professional files of Rice University professor of Musicology Marcia Citron. The collection contains essays, journals, newsclippings, magazines, programs, correspondence, conference ephemera, etc.
Biographical / Historical
Marcia J. Citron is Martha and Henry Malcolm Lovett Distinguished Service Professor of Musicology Emerita. A member of the faculty since 1976, Citron specializes in music of the Romantic era, opera, opera and film, gender in music, and Brahms. In addition to numerous articles she has authored five books, including two devoted to her current interest, media representations of opera: When Opera Meets Film (2010, Cambridge University Press) and Opera on Screen (2000, Yale University Press). Two earlier books garnered awards: Gender and the Musical Canon (1993) won the Pauline Alderman Prize for best book on women in music from the International Alliance for Women in Music; and Letters of Fanny Hensel to Felix Mendelssohn (1987) was named "Outstanding Book" by Choice magazine. Her other monograph is a Bio-Bibliography of French composer Cécile Chaminade(1988).
Citron's scholarly contributions have been recognized by a lifetime achievement award—the granting of Honorary Membership—from the American Musicological Society. She has served the AMS in a variety of roles: as member of the Board of Directors; chair of major publication-awards committees (for best book by a senior scholar, and for best article by a junior scholar); and member of several other committees, including the Colin Slim award committee, professional development committee, and status of women committee. Her research has been supported by grants from the National Endowment for the Humanities, DAAD (German Academic and Exchange Service), and Rice University.
(bio from Shepherd School of Music)
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the professional files of Rice University professor of Musicology Marcia Citron. The collection contains essays, journals, newsclippings, magazines, programs, correspondence, conference ephemera, etc.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Index Terms
Subjects
Women; Musicology--20th Century; Gender identity in music; Music -- Instruction and study; Music; Education
Document Types
programs (documents)
- Series I: Citron's scholarly essays, papers, and reviews, 1969-2014
  - "The Symphony" review. Notes Vol. 26 No. 1, 1969-09 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Corona Schröter: singer, compose, actress. Music & Letters Vol. 61 No. 1, 1980-01 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Catalogue of the Mendelssohn Papers in the Bodleian Library" Review. 19th Century Music, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Lieder of Fanny Mendelssohn Hensel." The Musical Quarterly Vol. 69 No. 4, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Felix Mendelssohn's influence on Fanny Mendelssohn Hensel as a Professional Compose." Current Musicology Issue 37/38, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "The Artist and the Women." The Musical Quarterly Vol. 71 No. 3, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Mozart's 'Abduction'." Opera Cues Vol. 28 No. 1, Fall 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Fanny Mendelssohn Hansel: Musician in her Brother's Shadow." The Female Autograph, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Marriage of Figaro: A Revolutionary Opera." Opera Cues Vol. 29 No. 1, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "The Marriage of Figaro: A Revolutionary Opera." Seattle Opera Magazine Vol. 7 No. 3, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Gender, Professionalism, and the Musical Canon." The Journal of Musicology Vol. 8 No. 1, Winter 1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Conference Reports. The Journal of Musicology Vol. 9 No. 4, Fall 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Gender and the Field of Musicology."Current Musicology No. 53, 1993-12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Publication and Music by Women." Sounds Australian No. 40, Summer 1993-94 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Zeffirelli's Otello and the Genre of FIlm-Opera." The Musical Quarterly Vol. 78 No. 4, Winter 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - International Conference on Music, Gender, and Pedagogics Compendium, 1996-04-26-1996-04-28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Classical Music and Postmodern Knowledge" book review. Journal of Musicological Research Vol. 16 No. 3, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Nineteenth-Century Music and the German Romantic Ideology" book review. J. Musicological Research Vol. 16, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 13th Nordic Musicological Congress Papers and Abstracts, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "The Performance of Visions in Peter Sellar's Television Production of Cosi Fan Tutte." Music, Seusatem, and Sensuality, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Opperatic Style and Structure in Coppola's Godfather Trilogy." The Musical Quarterly Vol. 87 No. 3, Fall 2004 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Feminist Waves and Classical Music." Women & Music Vol. 8, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Music, Gender, Education" review. Music & Letters Vol. 79 No. 3, 1998-08 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Shakespeare on Screen Conference Abstracts, 1999-09-21-1999-09-24 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Book reviews. Signs Vol. 26 No. 1, Autumn 2000 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Subjectivity in the Opera Films of Jean-Pierre Ponnelle." The Journal of Musicology Vol. 22 No. 2, Spring 2005 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Operatic Style and Structure in Coppola's Godfather Trilogy." Music & Culture, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Book reviews. Music & Letters, 2006-01 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Composers in the Movies" review. Music & Letters Vol. 88 No. 1, 2007-02 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Women and the Western Art Canon: Where are We Now?" Notes Vol. 64 No. 2, 2007-12 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "A Bicentennial Reflection." Nineteenth-Century Music Review, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "An Honest Contrivance: Opera and Desire in 'Moonstruck'." Music & Letters Vol. 89 No. 1, 2008-02 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "The Operatics of Detachment: Tosca in the James Bond Film 'Quantum of Solace'." 19th Century Music Vol. 34 No. 3, Spring 2011 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Verdi by Zeffirelli." Italian journal Vol. 20 No. 10, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Performance Practices Bibliography Supplement. Current Musicology X, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Series II: Citron's reviews and articles, 1985-2008
  - "Robert Schumann's Wife Clara." Houston Chronicle, 1985-09-22 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Rigoletto" review. Opera News, 2002-02 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Eugene Onegin" review. Opera News, 2002-05-03 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "The Barber of Seville" review. Opera News, 2004-07 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Madama Butterfly" review. Opera News, 2005-01 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "Idomena" review. Opera News, 2005-04 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Roméo et Juliette" review. Opera News, 2005-07 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "Boris Godunov" review. Opera News, 2006-01 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "L'Incoronazione di Popea" review. Opera News, 2006-07 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Simon Boccanegra" review. Opera News, 2007-01 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "Un Ballo in Maschera" review. Opera News, 2008-01 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Series III: Reviews, articles, clippings, 1980-2006
  - Publications. On Campus Rice University, 1980-10-17-1980-11-07 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Presentations. On Campus Rice University, Dec. 4 - Jan. 15, 1981-82 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - "Letters of Fanny and Felix Mendelssohn in the Green Books Collection at Oxford" review. The Journal of Musicology, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "The Letters of Fanny Hensel to Felix Mendelssohn" review. 19th Century Music Vol. 13 No. 1, Summer 1989 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Beyond Biography: Seventh International Congres on Women in Music, 1991-05-29-1991-06-02 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Book reviews. Notes Vol. 47 No. 3, 1991-03 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "The Sounds of Feminism" MS Vol. 3 No. 2, September/October 1992 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "On Musicology and Feminism." Stanford Humanities Review Vol. 3 No. 2, Summer 1993 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - "Canon Blast." Classical Music, 1993-10 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. New and Recent Titles in Music, Fall 1993 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. The Musical Times, 1994-01 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. Choice, 1994-01 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review, 1994-01-1994-02 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - "Music and Gender." Sallyport, 1994-02-1994-03 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. Studies on Women Abstracts, 1994-03-12 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - "The Asexual Muse." BBC Music, 1994-03 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - "Orchestrated Exclusion." Times Higher Education Supplement, 1994-04-22 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. Neue Zeitschrift Für Musik, 1994-04 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. The Journal of Musicology Vol. 12 No. 2, Spring 1994 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - "Reconsidering the Musical Canon." ILWC Journal, 1994-06 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. Musik, 1994-07 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. Music & Letters Vol. 75 No. 4, 1994-11 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. Notes Vol. 51 No. 2, 1994-12 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. Journal of the Indian Musicological Society Vol. 25, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. BRIO Vol. 31 No. 2, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. Haraa Vol. 17, Spring 1995 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. Book Review Digest, 1995-08 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" review. Signs Vol. 21 No. 1, 1995-08 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - "Dissecting the union between opera, film." Houston Chronicle, 2006-03-26 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - "Symposium to examine opera, film." Rice News Vol. 15 No. 28, 2006-03-30 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - "An opera you can't refuse." Houston Chronicle, 2006-07-23 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Rice Center for the Study of Women, Gender and Sexuality faculty research pamphlet. (Box 1, Folder 78)
- Series IV: Conference and presentation ephemera, 1981-2013
  - Duke University lectures, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - "Gender, Professionalism, and the Musical Canon" lecture flyer, 1988-11-16 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - "Music as Gendered Discourse" lecture flyer, 1991-02-04 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Feminist Theory and Music program brochure, 1991-06-27-1991-06-30 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" lecture flyer, 1993-03-10 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Feminist Theory & Music II conference program, 1993-06-17-1993-06-20 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" lecture flyer, 1994-10-04 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - "Gender, Voice and Fantasy in the Powell-Pressburger FIlm 'Tales of Hoffman'" lecture flyer, 1996-10-18 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Shakespeare on Screen conference certificate, 1999-09-21-1999-09-24 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - 13th Nordic Musicological Congress program - abstracts, 2000-08-15-2000-08-19 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - In and Out of Opera conference flyer and poster, 2000-10-27-2000-10-28 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Opera and Interdisciplinary Perspectives poster, Spring 2001 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - "Operatic Style in Coppola's 'Godfather' Films" presentation invite, 2006-03-01 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Intersections of Opera and Film Symposium flyer, 2006-04-01 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - The Shepherd School of Music spring events calender, Spring 2006 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - 18th Congress of the International Musicological Society conference certificate, 2007-07-10-2007-07-15 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - La Voix Dans Tous Ses États Autour de Stanley Cavell conference program, 2007-11-08-2007-11-10 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Opera, Exoticism, and Visual Culture conference flyer, 2008-09-25-2008-09-27 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - "Moonstruck: Film, Opera, and Art" lecture flyer, 2009-11-19 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - "Gender and the Musical Canon" lecture flyer, 2010-10-14 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Gender and Creation International Conference flyer, 2013-12-12-2013-12-14 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - A Celebration of Women and Music flyer (Box 1, Folder 100)
- Series V: Program Notes, 1971-2014
  - The Richmond Symphony, 1971-10-25 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - The Richmond Symphony, 1971-11-22 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - The Richmond Symphony, 1972-01-17 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - The Richmond Symphony, 1972-02-14 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - The Richmond Symphony, 1972-03-27 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - The Richmond Symphony, 1972-04-07 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - The Richmond Symphony, 1972-04-09 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - The Richmond Symphony, 1972-04-24 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - The Richmond Symphony, 1972-03-05 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Albert Tipton, flute, Mary Norris, piano, 1976-10-06 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Concord String Quartet, 1977-01-24 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Violin and piano sonata recital, 1977-03-02 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Retrospective: Chamber Music of Paul Cooper, 1978-11-30 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Houston Symphony Orchestra, 1986-02 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Symphony Science, 1986-02 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Houston Symphony Magazine, 1986-03 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Houston Symphony Magazine, 1986-04 (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Houston Symphony Magazine, 1986-05 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Houston Symphony Chamber Players, 1995-04-04 (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Houston Symphony Chamber Players, 1995-05-17 (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Houston Symphony Chamber Players, 1995-09-20 (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - Houston Symphony Chamber Players, 1995-11-30 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Da Camera of Houston, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - Houston Symphony Chamber Players, 1996-03-06 (Box 1, Folder 124)
  - Houston Symphony Chamber Players, 1996-09-18 (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - Houston Symphony Chamber Players, 1996-11-20 (Box 1, Folder 126)
  - Brahmsfest, 1997-10-27 (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Da Camera 13-14 Season, 2013-2014 (Box 1, Folder 128)
- Series VI: Correspondence, 1984-2014
  - Marcia Citron to Cornell University Press, 1985-09-26 (Box 1, Folder 129)
  - Marcia Citron to Linda Gardiner, 1994-07-05 (Box 1, Folder 130)
  - Kyra Davies thank you letter to Marcia Citron, 2007-05-06 (Box 1, Folder 131)
  - Christina Frangos thank you letter to Marcia Citron, 2005-05-02 (Box 1, Folder 132)
  - Christina Frangos letter to Marcia Citron, 2006-04-30 (Box 1, Folder 133)
  - Lauren Holmes Frankel thank you note to Marcia Citron, 2006-05 (Box 1, Folder 134)
  - Stephen M. Fry to Marcia Citron, 1996-11-07 (Box 1, Folder 135)
  - Stephen M. Fry to Marcia Citron, 1997-12-23 (Box 1, Folder 136)
  - Robb Fulcher to Marcia Citron, 2014-10-25 (Box 1, Folder 137)
  - Meghen Garvin to Marcia Citron, 2009-10 (Box 1, Folder 138)
  - Malcolm Gillis to Marcia Citron, 1999-05-20 (Box 1, Folder 139)
  - Lois Gurney to Marcia Citron, 2007-01-02 (Box 1, Folder 140)
  - Ellen T. Harris to Marcia Citron, 2014-11-19 (Box 1, Folder 141)
  - Anahid Kassabian letter to Marcia Citron, 1994-03-19 (Box 1, Folder 142)
  - Wendy Lin thank you note to Marcia Citron, 1997-12 (Box 1, Folder 143)
  - Maria Popova thank you note to Marcia Citron, 2012-05 (Box 1, Folder 144)
  - Jon Reeder to Marcia Citron, 1984-05-07 (Box 1, Folder 145)
  - Eva Rieger to Marcia Citron, 1994-03-14 (Box 1, Folder 146)
  - Samuel Schultz to Marcia Citron, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 147)
  - Don Whittaker to Marcia Citron, 2004-01-09 (Box 1, Folder 148)
  - Jen Woelfel to Marcia Citron, 2006-11-13 (Box 1, Folder 149)
  - Student thank you letter to Marcia Citron, 2006-04-27 (Box 1, Folder 150)
  - Thank you letter to Marcia (Citron) and Mark, 2006-05-21 (Box 1, Folder 151)
  - Thank you note to Marcia Citron, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 152)
- Series VII: Awards and Fellowships, 1993-2009
  - Pauline Alderman Award, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 153)
  - Distinguished Graduate Alumni. The Fountain, Spring 2003 (Box 1, Folder 154)
  - Rice University Humanities Research Center 2008-09 Fellowship Recipients (Box 1, Folder 155)
- Series VIII: Recital Performances, 1979
  - Advanced Recital program, 1979-02-01 (Box 1, Folder 156)
- Series IX: Photographs and tapes, 1993-1999
  - BBC-London, interview on "Gender and the Musical Canon", cassette tape, 1993-09-06 (Box 1, Folder 157)
  - Friends of Fondren Author's Reception photo, 1994? (Box 1, Folder 158)
  - Interview responses to Neuls-Bates questions, cassette tape, 1995-02-11 (Box 1, Folder 159)
  - Phone interview with Vera Calabria on Jean-Pierre Ponnelle, cassette tape, 1999-01-19 (Box 1, Folder 160)